<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians liue-loode Laid forth in a sermon vpon Math. 6. 33. By Samuel Hieron.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852247</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1687:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians liue-loode Laid forth in a sermon vpon Math. 6. 33. By Samuel Hieron.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64, 67-84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for William Butler, and are to be sold at his shop vnder S. Dunstanes Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 65, 66 missing in number only; text unaffected.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17561:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS <hi>Liue-loode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laid forth in a Sermon vpon <hi>Math.</hi> 6.33.</p>
            <p>BY SAMVEL HIERON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 10.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord will not famiſh the ſoule of the righteous.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>William Butler,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder <hi>S. Dunſtanes</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17561:2"/>
            <head>To my Worſhipfull good friend HENRY CHAMPERNOWNE of Modbury Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, that which of late I commended in a Sermon as a gift, to a couple of my friends, vpon their mariage day, as the beſt thing I had to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on them, for their then (as we call it) entring vpon the world, the ſame (being ouercome by intreaties to put it into print) do I here preſent to you, as a meet
<pb facs="tcp:17561:3"/>
implement for you at your now firſt beginning to keepe houſe. If God ſhall moue your heart (as I truſt he hath begun to do, and will more) to the entertainment of that Leſſon, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſubiect of this Sermon, it will bring that vpon you, which is onely able to make you rich, (<hi>the bleſsing of God</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 10.22.</note>) and be better to you then all that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate, which either you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready haue, or are in poſsibilitie hereafter to enioy Whatſoeuer of the worlds is now yours, either in poſſeſsion or in expectation, may be either waſted greatly, or loſt wholy, but that which <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note>,
<pb facs="tcp:17561:3"/>
is that <hi>durable riches</hi> which the <note n="c" place="margin">Pro 8.18</note> Wiſeman ſpeakes of, and that <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>good part</hi> which can neuer be withdrawne. As therefore in your childhood (in the ſeaſoning whereof with the rudiments of Religion &amp; Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, my ſelfe by Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence bare a part) by the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of your diſpoſition, and tractablenes in the beſt things, you gaue much hope, and haue ſince both anſwered and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it by ſhunning the atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call profanenes of theſe godles times, ſo goe on I pray you, and increaſe, &amp; whatſoeuer the guiſe of others be, who thinke religion is to be made ſhew of, no where
<pb facs="tcp:17561:4"/>
but at Church, yet lay you the foundation of your family, with the noble reſolution of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Ioſua, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioſ. 24.15.</note>. Hereof this Sermon may be vnto you, when you ſhall pleaſe to looke theron, a very fit Remembrance. Which I pray you, that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with you, as a pledge and teſtimonie of his ſincere loue, who intendeth no other but to be euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in his beſt affections,</hi> Sam: Hieron.</signed>
               <dateline>Modbury <date>
                     <hi>24</hi> No: <hi>1616.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17561:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 6.33.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But ſeeke ye firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſnes, and all theſe things ſhall be miniſtred vnto you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common guiſe at mariages,<note place="margin">The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Sermon at a Mariage gaue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble.</note> that the friends of the maried, do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them with gifts, to hanſell (as they call it) their entrance into that eſtate, and to furniſh them with ſome neceſſaries towards houſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore invited as a friend to theſe Nuptialls, and withall intreated as a Miniſter, to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the buſines with ſome word
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17561:5"/>
of exhortation, I thought it beſt to conforme my ſelfe (in this) to cuſtome; and to come in with my gift alſo, not of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and gold, but of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and mettall (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of) <hi>which is more precious than pearles, and with which all that can be deſired, doth not deſerue to be compared</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 3.15.</note>. And whereas the beſt things which men vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally beſtow, be ſuch as periſh with the vſe, are ſubiect to mothes and cankers &amp; theeues, and are not able to protect a man from that neceſſitie which is wont to <hi>ſurprize like an armed man</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 24.34.</note>; I ſhall recommend vnto you who are now entring vpon the world (if you pleaſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it) ſuch an implement, which ſhall (like the Arke to <hi>Obed-edom</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Sam. 6.11.</note>) bring a bleſſing vpon you and all yours, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17561:5"/>
you of that which all the wealth in the world cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, namely, that although you ſhould double the age of <hi>Methuſhelah,</hi> yet you ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer want a competency to maintaine you. <hi>Seeke yee first the kingdome of God and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be miniſtred vnto you.</hi> This in briefe for the reaſon inducing me to chuſe this text. Out of which as I ſhall deliuer that which will bee moſt for your good, and the ſureſt ſtocke for you to begin vpon, ſo I ſhall alſo teach that which ſhall bee for the beſt behoofe of euery one in this Aſſembly, that ſo none may goe away vnſpoken to. For the verſe it ſelf, (as it ſtands here in this Chapter, and is to bee viewed as a limme thereof) it is a Direction following vpon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17561:6"/>
a Correction.<note place="margin">The ſtate of the Text.</note> The correction, was for the abatement of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting &amp; heart-diuiding care for outward things. The dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is for the ordering of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans ayme and endeuour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that, which is the mayne of all. The thoughts of a man will be euer working, and they will bee alwaies actiue vpon ſome ſubiect. It was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough therefore for our Sauiour to take them of, and (as it were) to vnhange them from the world, vnleſſe hee did alſo, fix them other-where; Therefore lifting them from the world and the things thereof, he ſetts them to worke vpon the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; as honorable a remoue as was that of <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> from ſeruing in a priſon, to command as the ſecond in a kingdome. Thus in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17561:6"/>
teaching, Inhibitions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions muſt be coupled: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions to pull backe from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: Iniunctions to quicken to a better courſe. There were two voyces to <hi>Paul,</hi> the one, <hi>Saul Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act 9.4.</note>; the other, <hi>goe into the City and it ſhall be told thee what thou ſhalt do</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">ver. 6.</note>; not this, but this, to theſe two heads may a man refer all preaching. This for the conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion. Now for the Text: in euery mans eye and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it diuides it ſelfe into two parts:<note place="margin">The diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it.</note> The firſt I may call a Charge, binding vs to an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly care. The ſecond a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, becauſe it tends to the freeing of vs from a worldly care. In the Charge we are firſt to take notice of the ſubſtance of that dutie which is preſſed, and then next of a maine Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17561:7"/>
in performing it. The ſubſtance of the duty is to <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi> Here touching the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required, I ſhall not need to ſay much; I ſuppoſe wee are none of vs to ſeeke, what it is to ſeeke: Who doth not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it, to be a very diligent &amp; buſie kinde of enquiry; ſuch as was his in the parable for his <hi>ſheepe,</hi> or hers for her <hi>groate</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 15.48.</note>? Concerning the matter to bee ſought, it requires more ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; it is <hi>Gods kingdom, and his righteouſnes.</hi> For <hi>Gods kingdom,</hi> it is a terme in ſcripture:<note place="margin">What is the kingdome of God.</note> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more largely taken, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more ſtraitly: more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is that ample authority, and vnlimited ſoueraignty, which God hath and exerciſeth ouer all his creatures, both in heauen and in earth; wherof is mention
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17561:7"/>
Pſal. 103.19. <hi>The Lord hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared his throne in the heauens: &amp; his kingdom ruleth ouer all:</hi> more ſtraitly, it is that command ouer his Church, ouer his choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, his peculiar people; which is ſo often aſcribed to Chriſt, as he is the Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and vs: of this ſpake the Angell, bringing tydings of Chriſts birth, <note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 1.33.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the houſe of Iacob for euer, and of his kingdom there ſhal be no end:</hi> of this did <hi>Dauid</hi> prophecy in terming Chriſt <hi>the King ſet vp by God, vpon his holy mountaine Zion</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 2.6.</note>. God according to the election of grace hath called out ſome from the reſt of mankind, whom hee will ſaue, all that is done for the good of theſe is the kingdom of Chriſt. This king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is conſiderable either as it is in gathering and ſitting in this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17561:8"/>
life, (and is termed ſo the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace) or as it is in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment in the life to come, (and ſo is called the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory.) And this is <hi>the kingdome of God</hi> properly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded here;<note place="margin">What it is to ſeeke the kingdome of God.</note> ſo that to <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God,</hi> is, to endeuour by an entrance into grace, to gather aſſurance of an intereſt into glory.<note place="margin">What is the righteouſnes of God.</note> Now concerning that which is called <hi>the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God,</hi> which is here an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed as a thing to be ſought for with this kingdom; Know we this brifely that by it here, is not ment that eſſentiall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes whereby God is in him ſelfe righteous, which righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſomtime betokeneth his truth and fidelitie in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his promiſes (as 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9.) ſometimes his iuſtnes and vprightneſſe in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17561:8"/>
adminiſtration of the world, which is that doing right which <hi>Abraham</hi> ſpake of<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note>, but here the <hi>righteouſnes of God</hi> is taken much after the ſame ſenſe, as it is <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. &amp; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9 namely for that righteouſneſſe, by which man, who is a baſe, vile, and polluted ſinner in himſelfe, is accepted righteous before God, and is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in his ſight. This is called <hi>Gods righteouſnes,</hi> becauſe as it is acceptable to God, ſo it is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought in man by God through Chriſt, man conferring nothing therevnto. Now out of this righteouſnes, by which a man is iuſtified before GOD, ſtreameth another which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth it ſelfe by the fruits of righteouſnes before men; For thoſe whom the Lord by the righteouſneſſe of faith diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from the damnation of ſin,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17561:9"/>
the ſame he ſets at liberty by his ſpirit from the dominion of ſin; ſo that they haue their fruit in holines, ſo many as are in th'end to haue eternall life. This phraſe then touching the <hi>righteouſnes</hi> of this <hi>kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is added but as an illuſtration of the former. For to <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God,</hi> is to <hi>ſeeke the righteouſnes of God,</hi> that is, <hi>to ſeeke a paſſage through grace into glory, is to endeuour to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as righteous before God by Ieſus Chriſt, and to ſhine as a light in the way of righteouſneſſe among men.</hi> And this interpretation wipeth away that baſe calumny which <hi>Maldonate</hi> the Ieſuit in his Comment vpon this place vſeth againſt <hi>Caluin. Caluin</hi> ſaith that <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> may indifferently be referred either to <hi>God</hi> or to <hi>kingdome;</hi> wherevpon the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its triumph, becauſe <hi>(his)</hi> in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17561:9"/>
Greeke is of the maſculine gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whereas <hi>kingdome</hi> is the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine. whereof <hi>Caluine</hi> could not be ignorant; and therefore went not about to make a gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall agreement betwixt the words, but to declare a concord of ſenſe; and to ſhew (that which is true) that the <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods kingdome</hi> and <hi>Gods righteouſneſſe</hi> are all one; as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is. For that <hi>righteouſnes</hi> which becomes a ſubiect of this <hi>kingdome</hi> is ſuch, as by which there is iuſtification before God, and fruit of ſanctification before men. <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God</hi> require one and the ſame <hi>righteouſnes.</hi> And now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (as it were) paued a way for that which I am to deliuer, by giuing the ſenſe of the words, I come to that which is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this place; which is.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17561:10"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>That the things which concerne the ſoule, both for the preſent and future good thereof muſt bee enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after and ſought for with eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care.</hi> This is the very pith and marrow of this charge. We may ſuppoſe that we heard our Sauiour ſaying thus: <hi>You are full of care and thoughtfulneſſe about many things, your plots and proiects are ſpread, and ſtretched, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged many waies, what you ſhall eate, what you ſhall drinke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you ſhall bee clothed, you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your deſires like Hell which cannot be ſatisfied, and ſo that you might haue your full lading of the things of this preſent world, it ſeemes as if you would no more; one thing is truly and ſimply neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, and in it you be pittifully neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent; Behold God offers you a Kingdome, the glorie whereof (if you had eyes to ſee it) is able to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17561:10"/>
dimme and to obſcure all the glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering pompe of all earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to the meaneſt ſubiect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: not</hi> Salomon <hi>in all his royaltie is meete to be compared, the appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances whereto, and the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges whereof are ſuch as paſſe vnderſtanding, and do exceede all that you can aske or thinke, there is righteouſneſſe and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, pull away your ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eger and too violent indeauours from theſe baſer things, and fixe them vpon this; this is that onely thing which is worth the ſeeking for;</hi> Thus is the purpoſe of the place, thus is the doctrine. Now for the point it ſelfe, it ſhall bee no hard taske for mee, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it by the Scripture; what elſe but this endeauour and care for heauenly things, can bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in theſe terms of ſeeking for <hi>wiſedome, and knowledge as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17561:11"/>
ſiluer, of ſearching for it as for treaſure</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 2.4.</note>, <hi>of taking the kingdome of heauen by force</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Math. 11 10.</note>, <hi>of preſsing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 16.16.</note>, <hi>of labouring for the meate which endureth to euerlaſting life</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ioh 6 27</note>, <hi>of ſtriuing to enter in at the ſtraite gate</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 13.24.</note>, <hi>of running to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.24.</note>, <hi>of following hard toward the marke, for the price of the high calling of God &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 3.34.</note> 
               <hi>of giuing all diligence</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.15.</note>; what is here ment in all theſe but that <hi>ſeeking for the kingdome of God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> which is here perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Is not this that <hi>treaſure hid in the field, that pearle of great price for the parchaſe wherof all is ſold</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Math. 13 44 46.</note>, was not this it which <hi>Moſes</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued more <hi>then the treaſures of E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gypt</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 31.26.</note>, and which <hi>Dauid</hi> choſe rather <hi>then the abundance of wheate and wine, which the men of the world ſo much affected</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 4 6.7.</note>, and which <hi>Paul did account as loſſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17561:11"/>
and iudge as dung that hee might winne</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 3 8.</note> And why are the elect of God called a <hi>generation of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſa. 24.6</note>, but in reſpect of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries after this, according as it is the brand of the vngodly that they <hi>ſeeke not</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſa 10.4.</note>. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if either the excellency of a matter, or the neceſſitie therof, may be of force to perſwade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and to ſtirre vp care, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them is wanting, in the things which Chriſt here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends vnto our ſeeking. For excellency; The very name of a Kingdome argueth worth: the Deuill had hope to preuaile euen with Chriſt with the offer of Kingdomes <note n="a" place="margin">Luk 4.5.</note>, the addition of, <hi>God, (the kingdome of God)</hi> addeth to the dignitie, what thoughts are able to reach to the excellency of ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to which God is enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17561:12"/>
The kingdomes of the earth will endure no partners, there is one onely King, all the reſt be ſubiects. The limmes of this Kingdome are Kings all. Chriſt Ieſus <hi>hath made vs Kings vnto God euen his father</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Reu. 1.6.</note>, euen in this life they are all through him <hi>more then conquerors</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note>, and they ſhall each haue a <hi>crowne of righteouſneſſe at the day of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note>. Let vs looke a little, vpon the particular excellency of each degree of this kingdom. The kingdome of grace, which is his Church here on earth, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the preaching of the Goſpell; <hi>Glorious things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) thou cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 8.7.3.</note>, <hi>It is the ioy of the whole earth, the Cittie of the great King, in the palaces whereof God is knowne for a refuge</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ 48.2.3.</note>, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, <hi>are an holy nation, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17561:12"/>
company</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9.</note>, the people that dwell therein ſhall <hi>haue their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie forgiuen</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſ. 33.24.</note>, they are as <hi>the firſt fruits of his Creatures</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iam 1.18</note>, they which wrong them, <hi>euill ſhall come vpon them</hi> ſaith the Lord <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 2.3.</note>, <hi>God giueth his Angells charge ouer them</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſa. 91.21</note>, and <hi>is vnto them as a wall of fire round about</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Zach. 2.5.</note>, It is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Kings to bee nourcing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and of Queenes <hi>to be nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing mothers vnto it</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iſ. 49.23.</note>. Thus and more then thus, is the kingdom of grace. Now for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory, which way ſhall I beginne to declare the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it, when as <hi>the things, which neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare heard, neither haue entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of man, God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that loue him</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note>? This I may ſay in a word that looke what difference there is in proportion betwixt the Cope
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17561:13"/>
of heauen, and the earth, which reſpectiuely to it, is but as a pricke in the midſt of a Center, the ſame and much more there is betwixt the glory of all the kingdomes of the world vnited together (if it were poſſible) into one, and that which the Apoſtle calleth <hi>the glorie which ſhalbe ſhewed hereafter</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note>. Better with a kinde of ſilent aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to admire it, then to take on vs either to diſcribe it, or to comprehend it in particular. Now ſhall not ſuch a thing as this bee reputed worthy of our beſt care? What doe men many times to obtaine a <hi>corruptible crowne</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25.</note>, Strange things are done out of the deſire and hope of kingdomes. It is ſaid in ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that when <hi>Nero</hi> his mother being with childe with him; asked of the Aſtrologers what
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17561:13"/>
her ſonne ſhould come vnto, &amp; was told that he ſhould raigne,<note place="margin">Interimat modo impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note> but kill his mother, ſaid ſhe, <hi>Let him kill me ſo he may be King:</hi> thus ambitious was ſhee of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for her ſonne. This for the excellencie of the kingdom. Now the righteouſneſſe heere ſpoken of, it is excellent too, elſe why doth the holy Ghoſt call it a <hi>robe of righteouſneſſe, and a garment of ſaluation,</hi> with which who ſo is clad <hi>is decked like a brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, and tired as a Bride with Iewels</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iſ. 61.10.</note>, and how can that be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then excellent, by which an vgly ſinner, <hi>is made holy and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, and without fault in Gods ſight</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Col. 1.22.</note>. I haue briefly poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you to the excellency of the thing commended to our ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Now let me ſhew you the neceſſity too. The neceſſitie in a word is ſuch, that without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17561:14"/>
into this Kingdome, without partaking of this <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> there is no poſſibility for a mans ſoule to bee ſaued in the day of Chriſt. For vpon all thoſe that are without the pale of this <hi>kingdome</hi> ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted that ſentence, <hi>bring them hither and ſtay them before mee</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Luc. 19.27</note>, and <hi>know ye not</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>that the vnrighteous,</hi> ſuch as haue no righteouſneſſe, <hi>ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.</note>, and now, what ſaith Chriſt? <hi>What ſhall it profit a man, though hee ſhould winne the whole world and looſe his owne ſoule</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note>, were it not better for a man that hee had neuer been borne, then to haue his portion in the lake which burneth with <hi>fire and brimſtone which is the ſecond death</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Reu: 21.8.</note>? Look then of what neceſſitie, ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and happineſſe, and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17561:14"/>
is, of the ſame is this <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God,</hi> and this <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> here ſpoken of. If it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for a man to ſeeke to be ſaued, it is neceſſary to ſeeke the preſent and future good of his ſoule by laying the foundation of his hope of glory, vpon his now being in the ſtate of grace. What can deſerue the very beſt, and as it were the very quintiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a mans care if not this? Thus is the Doctrine. I come now to the vſe.</p>
            <p>The Vſe of this Doctrine,<note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> I will beginne with a reproofe; go on in with an exhortation, &amp; perfit with a direction. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe is of the generall, yea and the intollerable neglect of that, in which (according as hath been ſhewed) there ought to bee ſuch an eſpeciall care. Mens ordinarie carriage in and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17561:15"/>
about the matters of the ſoule, in and about this <hi>Kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of an opinion, that either it is one of the moſt needleſſe, or one of the moſt eaſie things that is, to be ſaued. If it were indeed the moſt ſuperfluous buſineſſe and ſuch as did aske the leſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for performance, I do not ſee how there could bee leſſe diligence and more cold ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours beſtowed about it then there is. Truth is, theſe are ſeeking times: euery man is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in ſeeking ſomething or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Here is one ſeekes for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, another for delight, another for reuenge, another for a newe faſhion; but how may a man runne (with <hi>Ieremy</hi>) too and fro by our ſtreetes and inquire, before hee can meete with one, who throughly and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17561:15"/>
ſeekes <hi>the kingdome of God</hi> and the appurtenances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto? For one ſerious and deep thought, about matters of an heauenly nature, we haue euen thouſands about theſe three worldly ſpecialties mentioned by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Epiſt. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>The luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life.</hi> Not a man among many, but would rather omit an oportunity for his ſoule, then not embrace an occaſion falling in at the ſame time, for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement of his commoditie, for the tickling and feeding of his delight, for the vpholding of that which hee termes his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation among men. It is a rare thing, when an earthly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, eſpecially when it carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an appearance and a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhew of ſome quicke and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible aduantage is made to giue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17561:16"/>
place, that ſo a meanes of good and edifying to the ſoule, may be entertained, but it is an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie thing to ſee ſpirituall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, in which God offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>his kingdome and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> vnto vs, iuſtled aſide, and made to ſtand by, for the ſake of a preſent contentment to the outward man; In one word, matters of the ſoule are ſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with that ſleightneſſe, with that ſeldomnes, with that remiſſenes, as if they were only of the By, and matters of the world are plyed with that eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with that induſtry, with that intention both of minde and body, as if they were the maine, or as if God had made man onely to that end to haue a portion in this life, and to graſpe in as much of the world as it is poſſible. Doth not this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17561:16"/>
deſerue reproofe? If in any thing a Preacher ſhould make <hi>his words like goads</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. 12.11.</note>, it may wel be in this; Folly is too gentle a terme to call it by, madneſſe in the higheſt degree, is not ſo foule a name as it deſerues: a man to beſtirre himſelfe with the ſtrength of his whole ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, for that which cannot adde ſo much as a dram me to his happineſſe, nay which may quickly hazard him in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, and in the meane time to put that to an aduenture which concernes the eternall good of his ſoule and body, can wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe what one name to giue it which may ſerue to expreſſe the groſſeneſſe of it as it is? vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand yee vnwiſe among the people, and ye fooles when will you be wiſe? with what charme might a man deuiſe to coniure
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17561:17"/>
out this retch-leſſe and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſpirit, which makes Hell to enlarge it ſelfe, by daily carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing headlong into it ſuch a world of ſoules. Let me entreat you, to doe your ſelues euery one that right, as to conſider your ſelues concerning this, to ſee whether this bee not your very fault, that you faile in care for the things that concerne the <hi>Kingdome of God,</hi> and that in you a baſe hungry care, for terrene commodities, doth euen eate vp and deuoure, the care of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, euen as <hi>the leane Kine,</hi> in Pharaohs dreame <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp the fat</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 41.20.</note>, and if it be ſo, then, ſay not to me as <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Eliah, haſt thou found mee ô mine enemie?</hi> but rather as <hi>Dauid</hi> did to <hi>Abigail, Bleſſed bee the Lord God of Iſrael which hath ſent thee this day to reproue me</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 25 32.</note>. Behold I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17561:17"/>
am here preſent before God, to heare whatſoeuer thou haſt to ſay vnto me from God, for the ſpeedy reforming of this great neglect. And ſo I come to the ſecond thing in my Vſe; the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; And here, I could wiſh, that I had ſome ſpeciall gift and power to perſwade, and that ſome ſuch law of grace were in my lips, that I might be among you this day as was <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> at <hi>Antioch</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act 11.23</note>, vpon whoſe words of exhortation <hi>much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ioyned themſelues vnto the Lord.</hi> And yet is it not ſtrange and pittifull, that in ſuch a caſe as this is, a man ſhould ſo much neede a perſwaſiue facultie? It were wonderful, if there needed much Rhetorique, to worke a ſicke man, to be willing to haue health, a poore man to bee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be made rich, a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17561:18"/>
man to bee willing to receiue a pardon; And yet ſuch an auerſnes is in our nature vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good, and ſo ſenſeleſſe are we of the beſt things, that a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in his meditations, is in no one thing driuen to ſo great a ſtraite, as to find out arguments and motiues, ſuch as may bee forcible inough to worke vs to this, that we would bee ſaued; and that we would embrace the offer of a kingdome. If thou <hi>kneweſt</hi> (ſaid Chriſt to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the well) <hi>the gift of God</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh: 4.10.</note>, and ſo if wee were aware of the worth of that which is tendred to vs, and how much the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the ſoule exceedeth all things elſe; a few words ſhould perſwade vs, Preachers ſhould haue ſmall neede to importune vs, and call to vs as <hi>Paul</hi> to them at <hi>Liſtra, O men why do ye theſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17561:18"/>
things</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 14 15.</note>, <hi>O yee houſe of Iſrael why will ye die</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ezek. 18.31.</note>, nay we would neuer leaue preſſing and vrging the miniſters of God with that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the perplexed Iaylor Sirs, <hi>what muſt we do to be ſaued</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 16.30.</note>. Let vs therefore bee ſtirred vp, I beſeech you, on all hands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this; you that haue bin vtterly careleſſe herein, &amp; haue ſcarſe beſtowed one earneſt thought vpon the things that concerne your ſoules, beginne now at the laſt to be more adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, do not any longer leaue this buſineſſe to an hazard, as if it were a matter of nothing to bee damned; Betwixt the not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Kingdome and the falling irrecouerablie into the Kingdome of eternall darknes, with the Deuill and his Angels, there is no third. And you that haue beſtowed ſome care this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17561:19"/>
way, be perſwaded to be ielous ouer your care, that it hath not beene ſo earneſt, ſo conſtant, ſo intentiue as it ought to be, learn now from hence foorth to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your care; and know that vnleſſe you be well acquainted with this, what a deale of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what inquiry, what ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing doth accompany religion, you are yet farre from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. He that cannot ſay out of perſonall experience, what an hard &amp; laborious taske it is to be a Chriſtian, hee ſhall neuer make me belieue that he hath any thing in him, ſaue a forme of godlineſſe. Seeking re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a care and an endeuour more then ordinary. Redeeme we as much time as poſſibly we may for this one thing, let vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge our ſelues rather in our outward profits and the purſuit
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17561:19"/>
of them, let vs rather want op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for our ſports, let all other things go to wrack rather then this one buſineſſe ſhould not be forwarded. Fie vpon it that ſo baſe a ſpirit ſhould poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe men, that they ſhould haue more minde to be ſlaues to the world, and ſeruants to vile affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions then to bee Heires of a kingdome. And thus is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing in my Vſe, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; of which becauſe I conceiue ſome hope in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, that it ſhall not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly bee in vaine, therefore I now come to the third thing, the direction. To exhort to ſeeking and not to inſtruct how to ſeeke, were vnprofitable; My direction therfore ſhal be reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to two things, 1. Where to ſeeke this kingdome, this righteouſneſſe. 2. How to know
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17561:20"/>
and bee aſſured that wee haue found it. Theſe two things I truſt of your ſelues and out of your owne reaſon you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to be very vſefull, and of great neceſſitie, ſo that I ſhall not neede to perſwade you to attention touching them. If you are affected with the loue of the commodity ſpoken of hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, you will bee glad to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand where to inquire it and how to bee reſolued, that you haue attained it. Concerning the firſt,<note place="margin">Where to ſeeke the kingdome of God &amp; his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</note> where this <hi>Kingdome, this righteouſnes</hi> muſt be ſought: both the one and the other muſt be ſought in the preaching of the Goſpell, which is proued by this that the Goſpell is called <hi>the Goſpell of the kingdome</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Math. 4.23.</note>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it declares both the nature of this <hi>kingdome</hi> and the way leading to it; &amp; then <hi>Paul</hi> giues
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17561:20"/>
this as a reaſon, why hee was not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt; becauſe <hi>by it the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God is reuealed</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.17.</note>. which two texts (not to inſiſt vpon any more) ſhew plainely that hee who aimes at the <hi>Kingdome of God,</hi> and at <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> muſt ſeeke it in the Goſpel. The diſpenſation of this Goſpel, God hath committed to his Miniſters; It is their office like <hi>Iohn-Baptiſt, to prepare by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to a kingdome</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Math. 3.2</note>, and <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to a man his righteouſneſſe</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iob. 33.23.</note>, viz. <hi>how being vile in himſelfe, he may ſtand and be preſented righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before God.</hi> Theſe things are plaine: God entending to call his elect out of the power of darkneſſe into the kingdome of his deare ſonne, <hi>hath appointed Paſtors and Teachers for their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.11.12.</note>, and meaning to make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17561:21"/>
them to become <hi>the righteouſnes of God through Chriſt hath ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Embaſſadors to beſeech, to pray,</hi> to treat with them in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor. 3 24.25.</note>, Behold then art thou perſwaded to <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeke it in the preaching of the word, or elſe there is no hope for thee to obtaine it. when I mention this meanes, I exclude not prayer (as ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thoſe that are ſo much for preaching to be enemies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prayer) I ſhut not out the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, I perſwade not a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of reading, nay I intend and inioyne theſe rather; No hope of good and comfort by a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, had he the tongue of men and Angells, if there bee not ioyned, Prayer to prepare to preaching, &amp; to be as the ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vpon the mowne graſſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17561:21"/>
preaching: Sacraments to ſeale vp the comfort, which is got by preaching: reading and meditation to confirme and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt that knowledge which is deriued through preaching, theſe thinges muſt not bee ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: God hath ioyned them, &amp; man may not ſunder them. But whoſoeuer he is, that thinkes he may well enough finde out the <hi>kingdom of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in the neglect or diſregard of the word preached, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that of no ſimple neceſſitie to that end, and ſo neuer ſtriues to enioy it, when hee wants it, nor cares to make the beſt vſe of it when hee enioyeth it, let that man make what ſhew hee will of deuotion, of reſpect to prayer, of honor to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of reuerence to reading, he doth vtterly beguile his own
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17561:22"/>
ſoule, &amp; ſhall be but as <hi>Solomons ſluggard, who luſteth, but his ſoule hath nought</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 13.4.</note>, or as the Prophets <hi>hungry dreamer, who in a dreame is eating, but is emptie when hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakes</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Eſ. 29.8. <hi>Lact. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</note>; it was truely deliuered of him who ſaid <hi>that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to finde out that which is ſought by a wrong way,</hi> and I am ſure the mouth of the Lord hath ſanctified beſides this no way, but of this I may boldly ſay this is the way, walke in it, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules; and againſt the forſakers of this path, I may as boldly denounce that of the <hi>Pſalm; ſuch as do turne aſide by their crooked waies them ſhall the Lord leade with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquitie <note n="r" place="margin">Pſ. 125.5.</note>, they do but waite vpon lying vanities and forſake their owne mercy</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 2.8.</note>. And this for the firſt thing in the direction; where to ſeeke. Now for the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17561:22"/>
next, how wee may know that wee haue found, and that our labour in ſeeking hath not been in vaine. Touching the <hi>kingdom of God</hi> firſt:<note place="margin">How a man may know he hath found the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> this is a ſure teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and a certain euidence that a man hath found it. A King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome erected in a mans owne breſt; I taught before how all that are admitted into this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, are Kings themſelues; that oyle of gladneſſe which was poured vpon Chriſt by which he was made the King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Gods elect, is like the oyle poured vpon Aaron, which ſtreamed thence to his beard, &amp; to the skirts of his garments, ſo is that diſperſed from him (the head) vnto al his members; and they are partakers with him of his royall dignity; and are Kings not only in reſpect of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing with him, ouer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17561:23"/>
but in reſpect of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt they haue ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, their fleſh with the affections and luſts being crucified, and they hauing by the power of Gods ſpirit gotten ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and maſtery ouer their owne hearts. Euery man natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally is a <hi>ſeruant vnto luſts</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 3.3.</note>, and yeelding obedience vnto ſinne, in the concupiſcence thereof, &amp; is a ſlaue vnto vile affections. Hee that is brought within the compaſſe of this kingdome by the power of the Goſpell, is in ſome meaſure diſcharged from this ſeruitude (<hi>for where the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is, there is liberty</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.17.</note>) and though he bee not ſtraight way come to that abſoluteneſſe of ſoueragnety ouer himſelfe, that there is in him no rebellion of the law of his fleſh againſt God, yet, he maintaineth a continuall
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17561:23"/>
and an implacable war againſt his own corruptions; ſo that by that meanes, as it is ſaid of the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Dauid, there was long warre betwixt the two, but Dauid waxed ſtronger and the houſe of Saul waxed weaker</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.1.</note>, ſo the old man, continually decai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, and the new man, becomes more potent. Here then, haſt thou beene a long and a diligent ſeeker of <hi>the Kingdome of God,</hi> by dependance vpon the Goſpell of the kingdome, and wouldeſt thou know, whether thou haſt found that which thou inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and ſo maiſt with comfort ſay with <hi>Deborah,</hi> to thy ſelfe, <hi>O my ſoule thou haſt marched vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly;</hi> ſee and inquire into thy ſelfe, how thou canſt rule thy thoughts, thy will, thy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the word of God, and by the ſpirit of God. It may be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17561:24"/>
in many things thou faileſt, but here is the queſtion; art thou dragged and drawne into euill as a captiue or doſt thou follow as a willing Seruant? Canſt thou truely ſay before God with whom there is no diſſembling, that the euill thou doeſt is that which thou wouldeſt not doe, and which thy heart is cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and for which thou car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt a kinde of indignation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelfe, and art therfore ſtill wraſtling and combating with thine owne vnruly moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſtriuing if by any meanes thou maieſt be able to ouerma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter them, I ſay to thee <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is within thee,</hi> and thou haſt found the thing which thou haſt ſought for. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if thou bee a ſeruant vnto thine own luſts, and art willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; deſirouſly taking thought
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17561:24"/>
for the ſteſh to content it, ſo that thine owne corruption is no burthen to thee, thou main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineſt no quarrell againſt it, thou contendeſt not with it, I ſay to thee, thou art a ſtranger from this kingdome: thou art a vaſſall of Sathan: and all thy profeſſion of religion is but meere hypocriſie. I haue giuen thee a marke, one of many, by which thou maieſt know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt found that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Let mee deliuer thee an other, by which thou maiſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand whether thou haſt found <hi>the righteouſnes of God</hi> yea or no. I could here inſiſt vpon that perpetuall companion of being accepted righteous before God, through Chriſt, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>peace towards God;</hi> by which is meant inward comfort in the aſſurance of reconciliation with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17561:25"/>
God through Ieſus Chriſt. But I commend this rather now for breuities ſake; viz. that <hi>the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God</hi> lookes two wayes; to God and to man: to God, ſo as there it preſents a man fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in his ſight; to men, ſo as it makes a man like <hi>Zachariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the eie of the world to liue <hi>without reproofe</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 1.6.</note>: what is that? to liue without iuſt chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge; I ſay iuſt challenge; for the moſt blameleſſe, are liable to vniuſt exceptions: Cruell witneſſes riſe vp, who lay to their charge, things which they neuer knew: but yet hee which hath found the righteouſnes of <hi>God</hi> (ſuch is the inſeparable v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion betwixt iuſtification and ſanctification) liues ſo, and by the grace of God, ſo hath his conuerſation in the world, that he is not found to liue in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17561:25"/>
practiſe of any one knowne ſpeciall ſinne. Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one therefore that would know touching himſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee hath obtained to that righteouſneſſe by which a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is acquitted before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall ſeate of God; inquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe for this, whether out of conſcience towards God and in deſire to adorne the doctrine of God, and to ſaue it from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill ſpoken of; hee careth to walke in the waies of <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> before men; Hee who bindes himſelfe to ſuch a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect walking, as that hee may keepe himſelfe vnſpotted of the world, and may ſhine like a light in theſe naughtie times, that man hath found <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God.</hi> He that is altogether diſſolute, walking in the waies of his owne heart, or
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17561:26"/>
elſe contents himſelfe with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall cariage, thinking (as the moſt doe) that it is not good to be too preciſe, and ſo vnder a color thereof takes ordinary li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to himſelfe in ſome things, which are not iuſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; that man is yet in his ſins, and hee is no other then a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſinner in the ſight of God. And thus I haue at laſt ended this vſe, and ſo the firſt point touching the ſubſtance of the duty giuen in charge <hi>ſeeke yee firſt the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is touching the manner or order of ſeeking: <hi>Seeke it firſt.</hi> Concerning which, this is the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct:</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>That the matters of God, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his glory and the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne ſoules, ought in all things to haue the preheminence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17561:26"/>
               <hi>Seeke firſt; This before all things, this aboue all things.</hi> The trueth hereof ſhall beſt appeare, if wee take view of it on this faſhion, viz. <hi>That heauenly things ought to be firſt in each mans life, firſt in ech day, and firſt in euery buſines. Firſt in each mans life. Remember thy Creator in the daies of thy youth <note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. 12.1</note>. It is good for a man to haue borne the yoke in his youth</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lam. 3.27</note>, euen <hi>a child muſt bee taught the trade of his way</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 22.6</note>. Was it not commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in <hi>Ioſiah</hi> that <hi>his heart was vpright before the Lord,</hi> when he was but eight yeares old <note n="d" place="margin">2. King: 22.1.2.</note>? was it not well that <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in the knowledge of the Scripture from a childe</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15</note>? If the firſt fruits <hi>be holy,</hi> is there not hope, that <hi>the whole lumpe will be ſo</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom 11.16.</note>. Haue you neuer heard of that obſeruation, touching <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons rod,</hi> that it was of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17561:27"/>
tree, and an Almond tree as appeares by <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.11.12. is <hi>of the trees which do firſt put out:</hi> he that will be for Gods purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes muſt beginne to blow and bud betimes. A baſe thing to reſerue the yeeres for the Lord, in which a man ſhall ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them. The put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off till then, is ordinarilie puniſhed either with a not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſeeke, or with a not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing to finde.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt bee <hi>firſt in each day. In the morning I will direct me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note>, <hi>I preuented the morning light, and cried for I waited on thy word</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 119.147.</note>. It is good to conſecrate a mans firſt awaking vnto God. Religious thoughts firſt let into the heart of a Chriſtian in the morning will keep it in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tune all the day. Drunkards <hi>riſe early to follow drunkenneſſe</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iſ. 5.11.</note>,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17561:27"/>
and euil men imagine <hi>wickednes on their beds that as ſoone as the morning light is come they may pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mic: 2.1.</note>. As they giue their firſt endeauours to the Deuill, ſo ſhould Gods ſeruants deuote &amp; diuert their firſt and their freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt meditations to his glorie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt bee <hi>firſt in each bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</hi> Our Sauiour would none of him, that would doe ſomething elſe before he would giue attendance vpon his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice <note n="l" place="margin">Luc. 9.61.62.</note>. The Magiſtrate muſt make this the firſt in his functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> comming to the crowne reſolued to <hi>deſtroy all the wicked of the Land, and to cut off the Workers of iniquitie from the Citie of the Lord betimes</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 101.8.</note>: and hee was aſhamed of himſelfe that he had beene ſo carefull of a conuenient houſe for his own eſtate, before hee had prouided
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17561:28"/>
a better place for the <hi>Arke of God to reſt in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.2.</note>. The Miniſter muſt make this firſt in his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, preferring Gods matters and his buſines before the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of his owne perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affaires <note n="o" place="margin">2. Tim 2.4.</note>, nay before his owne <hi>life</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 20.24.</note>. The ſeruing of his own turne muſt not be his maine end in entering into that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, but that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes of, euen that <hi>by all meanes he may ſaue ſome</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor 9.22.</note>. Hee that ſets on with the Maſterſhip and gouernment of a family, by entering into the ſtate of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke muſt make this firſt in his proceeding. His firſt aime muſt be, as Gods in the firſt inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of marriage, the encreaſing of Gods kingdome, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of Gods glory, <hi>by a godly ſeede</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Mal 2.13.</note> and that <hi>he may keepe his veſſell in holines and in honor</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.4</note>.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17561:28"/>
When luſt and couetouſneſſe be the leaders, a mariage is like an <hi>heritage haſtily gotten, the end whereof ſhall not bee bleſſed</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pro: 20.21</note>: In a worde it muſt bee thus in all things; for, <hi>whether ye eate or drinke or whatſoeuer ye do, do all to the glory of God</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1. Cor: 10.31.</note>. And is there not reaſon why it ſhould bee thus! who by ſo good right may challenge the precedence, as God may? <hi>In him we liue &amp; moue and haue our being</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note>, is it not of him that wee are able to ſeeke, and to whom is all due if not to him from whom all comes? ſhall not hee haue the prime of our daies, the flower of our wit, the beſt and ſtrength of all that is within vs, out of whoſe boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie we haue all, that we enioy? Well is it ſaid, that God being the <hi>Ancient of daies,</hi> may pleade a kinde of ſeniority, and by it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17561:29"/>
to be firſt ſerued. Then beſides, the things that concern the eternall good and happines of the ſoule are our chiefeſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, and the following &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of them, is the maine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand for which wee are come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world. God ſent no man into this world properly to mak himſelfe rich, to come to honor, or to ſate himſelfe, with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing contentments of this life, but the end of euery mans comming into the world is, that by glorifying of God here, hee may lay vp in ſtore a good foundation for the time to come. Now what man of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie vnderſtanding, but if he iourney into any place, hee will be ſure to doe that firſt which is of moſt moment? Suppoſe a man were occaſioned to trauell vp to <hi>London,</hi> to the Terme vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17561:29"/>
on ſome triall of his eſtate, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily he is requeſted being there to performe ſome kindneſſes for others, and it may bee hee hath a meaning, to buy ſome ſuch commodities as the place affords; but what doth he doe firſt, whereunto doth he princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally ſet himſelfe, will hee not firſt attend that, for which hee vndertooke the iourney, reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet that in ſome forward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, before he ſtirreth ſo much as a foot about ought elſe, when that is once done, then if any leaſure time fall out, hee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow that vpon his by-occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Is there not the like reaſon in this? A man is come here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, where in a ſmall ſcantling of time he hath many things to accompliſh, but yet ſuch, as are not all of like impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſome are but like ſeeing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17561:30"/>
of friends, or deliuerie of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or buying of trifles, or the like, falling into ſuch a iourney as before I ſpake of; there is one maine imployment, and that concernes the ſoule, it is like a grand triall at the law whereon hangs a mans whole eſtate; Is it not now agreeing to wiſedome, that this ſhould bee firſt follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, and applied with the firſt endeauour, that ſo if a man bee ouertaken by time, if any of his errands bee left vnfiniſhed, it may not be that, the not doing whereof, may turne to his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, and to his caſting away for euer and euer? What ſhould I labour to ſay more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this! Surely if matters of this kinde muſt bee ſought and cared for at all, they muſt bee ſought and cared for, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded firſt of all: and therefore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17561:30"/>
forbearing to make any further diſcourſe in ſo manifeſt a point, I will haſten to the Vſe.</p>
            <p>Here is matter inough for a large diſcourſe;<note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> it is euen inough to vexe the righteous ſoule of a <hi>Lot,</hi> to ſee what indignitie is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the things of God, and what folly is committed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourning theſe important buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, into the hindermoſt place. To equall <hi>Hagar</hi> with <hi>Sarah</hi> is iniurious, but to giue <hi>Hagar</hi> the place and to make <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> to come behind as an atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is intolerable. What ſaith our Sauiour? Is the ſeruant that hath beene abroad all day at worke, bid ſit downe and waited on, aſſoone as he is come home? Is he not commanded to attend firſt vpon his maſter and ſo to tarrie till his turne comes <note n="y" place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note>? How angry was God with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17561:31"/>
who tooke their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment firſt, in ſeeling them houſes, before they took in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the repairing of his houſe<note n="z" place="margin">Hag. 1.4.</note>, and how was the <hi>Prophet</hi> to exclaim vpon thoſe who were wont to offer the lame &amp; the ſick among their cattle for a ſacrifice <note n="a" place="margin">Mal. 1.8.</note>, as if any thing had bin good inough for God? Theſe things are types and ſhadowes, of that baſe vſage w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is to be ſeen in men towards God who ſeeme to account the very dregs &amp; refuſe of all to be good inough for him, of whom the beſt and the principall is not worthy. In ſteed of <hi>ſeeking the kingdom of God and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> in the firſt part of life, what more vſuall then to prorogue &amp; to put off this duty vntil the laſt act? That to which the dawning of a mans age is due, is poſted off vntil the euening, men not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17561:31"/>
how that <hi>folly</hi> (which as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 22.15.) <hi>is bound in the heart of a childe,</hi> will, if it be ſuffred to gather ſtrength by continuance, prooue ſuch a huge and vnruly lumpe, as will not ſoone bee ouermaſtered: hard is it to plucke vp that plant of corruption, which hath taken roote downewards. Me thinks when I eſpie an old man, that hath ſpent his younger daies in ſeeking of any thing rather then the thinges belonging to his ſoule, to bee to ſeeke how and which way to ſerue God aright and to be ſaued, hee is like one who hauing run out his youth in iollitie, is in the end put to his ſhifts and glad to begge for his liuing, when he is old. What a myſerie, when one ſhall bring his hoare head in ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the graue? and farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17561:32"/>
it is when one (through the iuſt hand of God) ſhall as hee hath liued in vanitie, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in impenitency, &amp; go out of the world as blindly, as hee hath gone on in the world ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturouſly. This is the iſſue moſtly of ſhufling the things of God and of our ſoules from the right place. Well; next, for <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the kingdome of God in euery day;</hi> I omit to vrge that which is beſt knowne to each mans owne ſoule, touching priuate communings with the Lord &amp; lifting vp the heart conſtantly towards him euery morning; I doe note onely the thinges that are obuious and apparant. Let the moſt houſes and families be a teſtimony how rare a thing it is to beginne the day with a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Lord by prayer. Surely if the Lord ſhould ſend
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17561:32"/>
an Angell of his wrath into ſo many houſes, as where this eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſeeking the kingdome of God firſt doth want, I belieue it would fare with many townes as it did with <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the night that <hi>Iſrael</hi> did depart, not an <hi>houſe</hi> (ſaith the text) in which there was not one dead <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 12.30.</note>. Think on it all you maſters of Families for your parts, and if you bee faultie, thinke whether to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this, can bee to <hi>ſeeke Gods kingdome firſt,</hi> and reſolue that there ſhall not a day paſſe more before you do reforme it. Gods curſe attends you in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you put your hands vnto if you leaue out this. Well, what ſay we to <hi>ſeeking this kingdome, firſt in euery buſineſſe?</hi> Let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with you Magiſtrates; whereto doe you principally &amp; mainely leuell your authoritie?
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17561:33"/>
I cannot accuſe you in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, but this is the generall guiſe, vpholding of credit, aduancing of profit, pleaſuring of friends, ſpiting of oppoſites, ſuch things as thoſe march in the foremoſt rancke, it is well if any thing, that concernes God and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, come in dropping at the later end; happily for forme &amp; cuſtome, or to get a name or to ſatisfie the importunity of a Preacher, ſome little matter is done that way: but where is he that makes this his firſt &amp; chiefe buſines? For one ſuch Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> that will lay all at the ſtake, that God may bee glorified by his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, an hundred ſuch as <hi>Gallio,</hi> that do not care for <hi>ſuch thingsc</hi>. There is as much iniurie offered to God, in our buſines of the miniſtery. Many an one there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17561:33"/>
is amongſt vs, who if hee were demanded, friend why cameſt thou hither? what firſt moued thee to become a Miniſter? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue if he ſhould tell (as we ſay) Gods truth, hee muſt confeſſe, it was more to liue then to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, rather to gather ſheaues into his owne barne, then to fill vp the Lords Garner; Surely that which hath the chiefetie in a mans deſire, will preuaile moſt in his endeauour, hee that is more buſie to feather his owne neſt, then to draw the people of Chriſt, as ſo many chickens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his winges, it cannot bee thought that in his putting his hand to the Lords plough, hee ſought for his righteouſnes and his kingdome firſt of all. What ſhould I ſay of other callings &amp; of other buſineſſes; what thinke wee (becauſe of the preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17561:34"/>
of marriage buſines) what if a man ſhould preſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all here that are married, &amp; in particular vpon the now newly married, what was the firſt ſought for matter in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall choyces? what was the firſt queſtion? what was the firſt inquiry? was it goods, or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, was it with what religion is the woman endewed, or with what portion is ſhee endowed? ſurely that which moſt mooues both parents in their direction and parties to bee married in their election, is rather portion and proportion, then ſinceritie of heart and well grounded pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards God. Hence comes that roote of bitterneſſe which groweth vp betwixt the moſt couples; where religion was not the firſt motioner, the iſſue of the mariage without great
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17561:34"/>
repentance can neuer bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. A wofull thing, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to haue a Husband, that cannot dwell with her as a man of knowledge: a lamentable thing a man to haue a Wife, whom hee cannot comfortablie loue not only as a woman, but as an Heire together with him of the grace of life. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this vſe. It is not inough you ſee that wee take care for heauen, but we muſt giue it our firſt, our beſt, our ſtrongeſt care. I wiſh this to you all that heare me, but eſpecially let mee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to thoſe whoſe nuptials we are here met together to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize; you are both younge, and as your education hath bin, I truſt, in the feare of God, ſo be ſure ſtil to conſecrate theſe your firſt and flouriſhing daies to Gods glory, and to the things
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17561:35"/>
which concerne your ſoules. Be not now firſt for profit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light meaning to reſerue your grauer yeares for grauer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. You know not what a day may bring foorth; euen childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and youth are vanitie; and for euery particular day remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to beginne it priuately with the Lord, and if God giue you a familie let all your buſineſſes take their beginning at ſome ſuch ioint ſeruice, as may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for you that the glory of God and the pleaſing of him is your chiefeſt aime. If euer God ſhall raiſe you to ſome higher place, in which to gouerne publikely, then call to mind the precept giuen you on your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage day, and binde your ſelfe to be more for Gods glory and for the vpholding of his honor, then for any other reſpect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17561:35"/>
and if you haue failed in your proceedings hitherto, not being ſo carefull, touching the religion either of other as was fit, deſire God that it may not be layed to your charge, and ſtir vp your ſelues to make a kinde of recompence therein by a conſtant care more to ſeeke and more to eſteeme a dramme of grace and a mite of ſinceritie, then all that euer elſe the world is able to afford you. And the more to encourage you to this; I come from the firſt part of my text, the charge, to the ſecond, the diſcharge <hi>And al theſe things ſhall be added vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The plaine point of Doctrine thus ſtands.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct:</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>That they which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſeeke for heauenly things, ſhall not be left vnſupplied of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. Here is a ſtirre</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>for the things of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17561:36"/>
the world, and you lay about you, as if the duſt of the earth, ſhould not ſuffice for euery man to take an handfull, and all your drift is, that you may haue inough for preſent maintenance; Behold I will ſhew you a more excellent way, I preach ordinarily to you of a kingdome, I tell you of the righteouſnes of God, ſeek you that in ſuch ſort and maner as you ought; Lo, all theſe things wil come in of themſelues, it may be not in the meaſure you would; but in ſuch a proportion, as your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father knowes to be conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</hi> Look as the ſhadow follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man ſtil, which turneth his face toward the Sunne, ſo theſe things neuer but attend vpon thoſe that ſet their thoughts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heauenly things. What a world is there for this in holy Scripture? God long ago made a promiſe vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> that if
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17561:36"/>
he would walke with him <hi>and be vpright</hi> (which is all one with that <hi>ſeeking</hi> here made mention of,) <hi>he would be a God to him, and to his ſeede after him</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note>. Now how can a man be left deſtitute whoſe God the Lord is? who both knowes ones need (for <hi>all things are naked and open vnto his eyes</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note>) and is all-ſufficient; <hi>The earth is his and all that therein is</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 24.1.</note>, and whoſe loue paſſeth the loue of naturall parents? It is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a woman <hi>to forget her child, and not to haue compaſsion on the Sonne of her wombe, but hee cannot forget</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſ 49.15.</note>, <hi>his compaſsions faile not</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lam. 3.22.</note>. The like promiſe was after renued vnto <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">chap. 1. 5.</note>, and the Apoſtle teacheth euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer to account himſelfe to haue an intereſt in it <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 13.5, 6.</note>, <hi>I will not faile thee nor forſake thee.</hi> How often doe we read ſuch things
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17561:37"/>
as theſe: <hi>The eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that truſt in his mercy, to deliuer their ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in famine</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſ. 33.18, 19.</note>. <hi>The Lyons do lack &amp; ſuffer hunger, but they which ſeeke the Lord, ſhall wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nothing that is good</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note>. <hi>No good thing ſhall he withhold from them that walke vprightly</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 84.11.</note>. <hi>The Lord will not famiſh the ſoule of the righteous</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Prou. 10.3.</note>. <hi>The good man ſhall giue inheritance vnto his childrens children</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 13.22.</note>. That ſpeach of the prophet <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> three times repeated in the New Teſtament; <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by his faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 2. 4.</note> hath reference as well to the life of the body in this world, as well as to the ſpirituall life of the ſoule. Faith is as it were, the liuely-hood of a Chriſtian; It is the ſtocke whereon he liues, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it giueth him an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17561:37"/>
not to be caſt off. Chriſt had a meaning to teach this, euen in the courſe and order of the Lords prayer, in ſetting that, of <hi>Hallowed be thy name, Thy kingdome come</hi> &amp;c, before that concerning <hi>daily bread,</hi> that wee might build our expectation of being heard in the latter, vpon the truth of our deſire for the former. And indeed if we enter into a due conſideration of the point, we muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be a truth. He that <hi>ſeekes the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſhall not miſſe of the end of his deſire in that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly benefit. For <hi>God will ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the deſires of them that feare him</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 145.19.</note>. If God will giue the more excellent, will he deny the things of leſſer value? <hi>Fe are not</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>your Fathers will is to giue you a kingdome</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Luc. 12.32.</note>: will he
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17561:38"/>
who will beſtow a kingdome, not beſtow neceſſary comforts for the outward man? Will he who <hi>giues Chriſt, not giue with him all things alſo</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ro. 8.32.</note>? Whom thinke wee to be reſpected by God, he that <hi>ſeeks his kingdome,</hi> or the foules of the ayre, the beaſts of the forreſt, the lillies of the field, to day freſh, to morrow in the fornace? Surely the ſeekers of his <hi>kingdome, are his chiefe treaſure</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 135.4</note>. <hi>He delights in them</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 147.11.</note>. <hi>He dwells with them</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 14.23.</note>. <hi>He keeps their bones</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 34 20</note>, <hi>their haires</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Math 10.30.</note> 
               <hi>their feete</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.9.</note>. Conſider then, <hi>He giues beaſts foode, and the young Rauens that cry</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ 147.9</note>, <hi>he lookes after the ſparrowes</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Matt 10 29</note>, <hi>he takes care for oxen</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 9 9.</note>, <hi>he clotheth the graſſe</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 6.30</note>. How is it poſſible that hee ſhould neglect thoſe whom his ſoule loueth, yea for whoſe ſakes euen <hi>Kings are reproued</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 106.14</note>, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17561:38"/>
which <hi>are to him as the apple of his eye</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Zac 2 8.</note>. Strange, but yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable are the euidences and examples which the Scripture affords of Gods prouiding for his in outward things. The Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens firſt and laſt, at morning and euening brought bread and fleſh to <hi>Elias</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 17.</note>; by him and for him God made that ſmall por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of oyle and meale which the widdow had to laſt out to the end of the famine. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided ſtrangely for the widdow of the prophet, when the cruell Creditor was come to take her ſonnes to be his bondmen <note n="i" place="margin">2 King: 17.</note>. He found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meanes for <hi>Iacob</hi> and his family in the dearth; <hi>he had ſent a man before</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 105.17.</note>. It is memorable which befell our Sauiour, and is doubtleſſe written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. He was borne in a poore eſtate, his mother could finde
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17561:39"/>
no roome in the Inne, it ſeemes ſhee was in want, otherwiſe money would haue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more reſpect. The home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne people (as it is likely) tooke no notice of her want. Now ſee how God, who is a God at a pinch, brought the Wiſe-men from farre, with their preſents, <hi>Gold, incenſe, &amp; myrhe</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Mat 2.11.</note>. A notable example of Gods prouiding, when it is leaſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and where there is the ſmalleſt likely hood. When <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> fled from <hi>Abſolom</hi> and went for his life, and had ſmall leaſure to take prouiſion with him; ſee how God prouided, <hi>Shobi the ſonne of Nahaſh, and Machir the ſonne of Ammiel, and Barzelai brought wheat and barley &amp; flower and beanes and parched corne</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. Sam. 17 27.</note>. I remember what Chriſt ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>When as I ſent you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17561:39"/>
without bag and ſcrip, lacked ye any thing? and they ſaid nothing</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Luc. 22.35.</note>. What ment our Sauiour in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe miraculouſly that followed him from place to place to heare his preaching, but to giue aſſurance thereby, that they which ſeeke heauen as they ought, ſhall neuer be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here on earth; they ſhall neuer be oppreſſed with wants for their bodies, who are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to make prouiſion for their ſoules. But now this doctrine may ſeeme not to be generally and vniuerſally true without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. For many deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and many forward men in religion, haue beene and are in great want, and may ſo be, as is gatherable out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of <hi>Lazarus</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Luc. 16.</note>, who would haue beene glad of a few crums, or to haue licked a trencher;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17561:40"/>
and, I do not ſee ſaith the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, any of them all a penny the richer, for all their earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It is anſwered. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and point vndertaken here to be proued, is not, that they which <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God and his righteouſnes,</hi> ſhall neuer be poore, ſhall neuer be ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for outward things, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be brought euen to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of bread. I know how the prophets of God were glad of bread and water in a hole vnder ground, when the prophets of Baal were fed at <hi>Iezabels</hi> table <note n="p" place="margin">1. King. 18.4, 19.</note>. Many deare ſeruants of God, doe with <hi>Michaiah</hi> feed vpon the bread and water of affliction; when as they who walke on in their ſinnes, drinke wine in boules, eat the lambes of the flocke, and the calues out of the ſtall, and haue as much as heart
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17561:40"/>
can wiſh. So the poore <hi>Iewes in Shuſan were in perplexity, when the King and Haman ſate drinking in the Palace</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Heſt 3.15.</note>; and diuers of the Lords worthies were deſtitute and afflicted <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 11.37.</note>. But here is that, which is hence proued, that he whoſe heart is ſet to <hi>ſeeke the kingdome of God firſt and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,</hi> though he may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, yet he cannot be ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though he may be in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, yet he cannot be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of pouerty; <hi>though he may be caſt downe, yet he ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.8, 9.</note>, <hi>he ſhall neuer be left com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 14.18.</note>, he ſhall alwaies haue a ſecret comfort to ſweeten all his outward burdens. When hee hath a ſmall proportion, hee ſhall be taught <hi>how to want</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Phil 4.12</note>, he ſhall euer <hi>eat to the contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his minde</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Prou. 13.25.</note>. His little, his pulſe, his dinner of green herbes,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17561:41"/>
ſhall relliſh better with him then their plenty, to whom euery day is a day of ſlaughter, Gods countenance being lift vp ouer him puts more ioy into his heart, then the ſmalnes of his portion can giue diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Once he is ſure he ſhall haue inough for the preſent, I meane inough for the neceſſity of nature, and comfort with it, and greater plenty when the Lord doth ſee it to be more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. Thus then wee muſt vnderſtand it. <hi>All theſe things ſhall be miniſtred vnto you, foode, rayment &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt meaneth not, that God will cloth euery ſuch one in ſilke, or feede him with dainties, or giue him a houſe of Cedar with pillars of marble to inhabite in, but hee will meaſure him ſuch a portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe, as he ſhall know to be
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17561:41"/>
expedient, and euen the ſcanteſt portion ſhall be ſweetned with the gracious feeling of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Thus is the doctrine.<note place="margin">Vſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Mee thinks in this point I ſhould haue euery mans atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Who would not be glad to heare of ſuch a ſtocke for his maintenance here in the world, as ſhall neuer bee conſumed. Euery man affecteth perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. He who hath a leaſe for yeeres thinkes himſelfe well; he who hath an eſtate for his owne life and his childs is in his owne opinion better; but hee who hath got the fee ſimple eſtate, hee (he imagineth) needes not care. Theſe be things whereon men build their hopes, but (alas) is it not poſſible that for all this a man may fall into an extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? what though a man hath ioyned houſe to houſe, and field
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17561:42"/>
to field, vntill there be no room? what though his grounds bring forth fruit plenteouſly, his barnes bee filled with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, his ſheepe yeeld out thouſands and ten thouſands in the ſtreets? what if hee haue ſo much ſtocke, ſo many ſhips tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding here and there, ſo much cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine comming in; what though in a word he were as rich as <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Emperor, of whom <hi>Auſten</hi> reports,<note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei l. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>God had fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him with ſo many and ſo great earthly commodities, that no man might dare to wiſh the like;</hi> is ſuch an eſtate ſo fenced in, or ſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by any perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree that it cannot be diſſolued? Is not the truſt in theſe things <hi>like the houſe of a ſpider</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iob 18.14.</note>, <hi>which though it doe take hold vpon the rafters, yet is ſodenly ſwept downe with a broome. The Lord ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17561:42"/>
looſeth the coller of Kings &amp; powreth contempt vpon Princes</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Iob 12.18</note>, and ſweepes away euen great houſes, as a man <hi>ſweepes away dung till all be gone</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. King. 14.10.</note>. All the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Lawyers in a kingdom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deuiſe how to ſecure a man for hereafter. See here a new leſſon how to be made ſure of meate and drinke and clothing while we liue. Here is a portion like that which the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Babel</hi> gaue to <hi>Iehoiachim, a continuall portion, euery day a certaine, all the daies of his life vntill he died</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 52.34.</note>; <hi>Seeke yee first the kingdom of God</hi> &amp;c. This deed was drawne vp in heauen, engroſſed by the pen of the Euangeliſt in the goſpell, ſealed by the bloud of the Lord Ieſus, who witneſſed a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion vnder <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> who neuer yet did, neither euer will beare witnes to a falſhood, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17561:43"/>
let all the world be examined, it ſhall not be able to afford one inſtance of the failing of this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance. How glad men be when their Lords haue ſealed their leaſes, how pretious be their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidences and tenures of land, how ſafely they are kept that they may not bee embelezed? How all you Merchants reioyce at the ſafe arriuall of a ſhip, &amp; at the report of a boone voyage? how ſecure begin we to be in our thoughts, when we ſee ſom what vnder hand; why ſhould we not with ioy lay it vp in the midſt of our hearts, which ſhall ſecure vs of a better portion, then the greateſt King of the earth is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beſtow? If the King ſhould giue thee a penſion or annuity out of his Exchequer for thy life it were much, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of it thou canſt not ſurely
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17561:43"/>
ſay, thou ſhalt not want. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe cannot miſſe, his word who made it doth endure for euer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe himſelfe liueth euer to make good his word, and it is impoſſible for him to deny himſelfe. And here ſee (I pray you) how far the thoghts of God are differing from our thoughts, and his waies from our waies. Mens common thoughts are that if religion ſhould be thus cared for before all other things; if they ſhould prefer matters appertaining therevnto before things of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, it were the next way for them to be quite vndone. For what is mens ordinary reaſon, why they doe redeeme ſo little time from the world for holy purpoſes, and why they take ſo much euen of the Lords day to giue vnto themſelues? Is it not this, elſe (ſay they) we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue? Hence is it that <hi>the kingdom of God</hi> which ought to bee firſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17561:44"/>
ſought, is (as I haue ſhewed) caſt backe into the loweſt place. Men thinke it wiſdome firſt to be ſure of the world, before they looke after heauen; firſt prouide for the body, then for the ſoule; firſt ſeeke an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate here, then caſt for an eſtate hereafter. This is the common courſe: wherevpon it is that there bee many who haue liued long in the world, and haue laboured hard, and toyled infinitely to get a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, are yet ignorant which way to <hi>ſeeke for the kingdome of God;</hi> nay they haue ſcarſe ſo much as a thought of it, or a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit or knowledge, what it meanes: <hi>What is the kingdome of God, what is the righteouſnes of God,</hi> how many old men, how many rich men, how many painfull men, who haue euen worne out themſelues with catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the world, if they were put vnto it, know not what to anſwer?
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17561:44"/>
Let vs yet at the laſt all of vs, and you eſpecially, for whoſe ſakes prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally this daies labour is, learne this wiſdome, from the God of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, out of the booke of wiſdom, which is able to make vs wiſe vnto ſaluation. Begin we not ſtill at the wrong end; firſt the world, then heauen; firſt gaine, then godlines; firſt riches, then religion; firſt the backe and the belly, and then the ſoule; but let vs take the true courſe both for contentment here, and for ſaluation hereafter: make it your firſt care, your chiefe care, and in compariſon your onely care, how to become members of <hi>Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> how to attaine to that <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes</hi> without which the <hi>kingdome</hi> cannot be enjoyed; Either we muſt deny the truth of God ſpeaking in his word, and ſay that he feedes and foades vs of with vaine words not to be beleeued, or els yeeld this to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17561:45"/>
be a truth, that this is the alone way to get a comfortable ſecurity for outward things. Thus it is as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzene</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nec prodi, nec perdi.</note> 
               <hi>It is profit indeed to get gaine to a mans ſoule.</hi> This is that wealth, which (as one ſaith) <hi>can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be betrayed nor loſt.</hi> He who hath it not is a miſerable and an accurſed begger in the midſt of abundance, and he who hath but as much of it as a graine of muſterd-ſeede is an abſolute rich man, euen when hee hath nothing. The world will not beleeue this, yet is wiſdom iuſtified of her children. <hi>They which are after the fleſh ſauour the things of the fleſh, &amp; they which are after the ſpirit the things of the ſpirit</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ro. 8.5.</note>.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17561:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
